Guide to the Socialist Party (U.S.) Correspondence TAM.056.009
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Socialist Party Correspondence
1902-1947
TAM.056.009
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
5.25 linear feet (11 boxes)
The Socialist Party of America was established on 29 July 1901 as a result of a merger between the moderate wing of the Socialist Labor Party and the Social Democratic Party. For most of its turbulent history, the Socialist Party has been reformist in its political attitudes and democratic in its organization. Until the mid 1950s, the Socialist Party advocated trade unionism, supported an evolutionary rather than a revolutionary conversion to socialism, and endorsed progressive, as well as, socialist candidates for public office. In addition to the sizable amount of correspondence, the collection also contains minutes, mimeographed reports, bulletins, constitutions and by laws, financial papers, ephemeral printed matter, circular letters, form letters, political platform statements, lists, resolutions, memoranda, and press releases. The bulk of the material is from the New York City and New York State organizations, respectively, and coverage is strongest for the factional struggles of the early to mid-1930s between the "Old Guard" and the "Militants." Note: this collection has been microfilmed, and researchers must use the microfilm copy (R7124, reels 13-14).
Socialist Party (U.S.).
Box 1-11
Existence and Location of Copies note
This collection is available on microfilm (Film R-7124, Reels 13-14) for use in this repository only. Researchers must use microfilm for this collection.
Provenance
Transferred from Rand School Archives, 1962.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. However, patrons must use microfilm (Film R-7124, Reels 13-14).
Historical/Biographical Note
The Socialist Party of America was established on 29 July 1901 as a result of a merger between the moderate wing of the Socialist Labor Party and the Social Democratic Party. For most of its turbulent history, the Socialist Party has been reformist in its political attitudes and democratic in its organization. Until the mid 1950s, the Socialist Party advocated trade unionism, supported an evolutionary rather than a revolutionary conversion to socialism, and endorsed progressive as well as socialist candidates for public office.
Between 1901 and 1912, the party's membership grew from 10,000 to 118,000 and the votes cast for socialist Presidential candidates increased proportionately from 100,000 to 900,000. By advocating reform of the political and economic system, the party was able to enlist the support of many orthodox socialists and many heterogeneous elements remaining from such progressive movements as the Greenbackers, Populists, and "Single Taxers". The result was a broad based party, particularly strong in the West, which was prepared to sacrifice ideological purity for numbers and revolutionary gains for immediate political success. Evidence of this policy was demonstrated in the fact that in 1912 there were 56 socialist mayors, over 300 socialist aldermen, many socialist state legislators, and one socialist member of the House of Representatives.
This success, however, was short lived. Throughout the 1910s and 1920s, the Socialist Party suffered from the same external pressures which caused other progressive movements to stagnate. The party also suffered from numerous internal crises as well. Three major conflicts which caused the party to decline in this period were: (1) the expulsion of its revolutionary wing in 1912 1913; (2) the party's official opposition to World War I, which not only alienated the conservative membership of the party but also led to the trial and imprisonment of such important party figures as Eugene V. Debs and Victor Berger; and (3) the Russian Revolution of 1917, which encouraged the left wing of the party to demand a more militant program and, when this was not forthcoming, to secede from the party in 1919 and establish the Communist Party.
Following a brief resurgence in the late 1920s and early 1930s under the strong leadership of Norman Thomas, the Socialist Party was once again plagued with internal conflicts. The principal divisions within the party at this time were generational, geographical, and ideological in nature. These divisions were manifested in three major factions within the party. First, there was the "Old Guard" which was composed largely of middle aged and elderly members who had been in the party since its early years. The Old Guard occupied most of the party's leadership positions, including the office of national chairman and the National Executive Committee. Geographically, the old Guard was strongest in Pennsylvania, New York, and Connecticut, but it also controlled many of the state offices across the country.
Opposing the Old Guard were the "Militants" who were young, doctrinaire Marxists and the "Progressives" who were young, radical nonMarxists. The Militants, who resided primarily in New York City, were not communists. In fact, they were opposed to the Communist Party and they were critical of the Soviet Union's denial of civil liberties. The Progressive faction in the Socialist Party, also from New York City, was not so powerful as the Old Guard, but it was larger in size than the Militants. The Progressives, for the most part, were not Marxists. Instead, their goal was to organize a farmer labor party which would be based on principal rather than political expediency.
These three factions did not bring their differences of opinion into public focus until the 1932 Socialist Party convention in Milwaukee. During this convention, however, the groups clashed over the re election of Morris Hillquit as national chairman and two resolutions concerning the Soviet Union and trade unionism.
The conflict intensified during the New York City fur workers dispute in 1933. In the fur industry of New York City there were two rival unions, one controlled by the Old Guard and the other led by the Communist Party. During the dispute over which union should represent all of the fur workers, the Militants charged that the Old Guard was attempting to subvert the communist union in its quest for total control despite the fact that most of the workers supported the communists. Norman Thomas concurred in this view and demanded that the Old Guard cease its activities against the communist union members. The Old Guard union responded to these charges by obtaining a labor injunction against the communist union. Eventually, the fur workers dispute was resolved when members of both unions negotiated a settlement.
Another incident which pitted the three factions against each other occurred during the debate on the Declaration of Principles at the 1934 Socialist Party convention in Detroit. The Declaration of Principles was drafted by the Progressives and the Militants and included numerous statements on issues which they believed every socialist should advocate. During the debate on this document, the factions argued over the statements pertaining to socialist action in the event of war and the socialist view of democracy. When the delegates finally adopted the Declaration of Principles before the convention adjourned, it clearly demonstrated that the Old Guard was gradually losing control of the party.
The factional strife came to a climax in 1936 when the Old Guard bolted from the Socialist Party after the national convention in Cleveland and organized the Social Democratic Federation. The withdrawal of the Old Guard was a serious loss for the party. Not only did major socialist figures from New York, Connecticut, Maryland, and Pennsylvania leave the party, but they took with them much of the financial support of the party as well. In addition to these developments, two major urban political machines in the Socialist Party Reading, Pennsylvania and Bridgeport, Connecticut joined the Social Democratic Federation.
Following the departure of the old Guard, the Progressives and militants continued the party's infighting by dividing into three groups. The first group was an amalgamation of the old Progressives and the leadership of the Militants. Under the direction of Jack Altman and Paul Porter these moderates supported the American Labor Party and endorsed a more democratic view of socialism. A second group, formerly associated with the Militants, were emerging as the new left wing faction of the party. Calling itself the "Clarity" group after the periodical, Socialist Clarity, this group was led by Frank Trager, Gus Tyler, Robert and Max Delson, and Herbert Zam. Ideologically, the Clarity group was not opposed to labor parties and farm labor coalitions, but they were more insistent than the Altman group that any labor party wanting Socialist Party support should have a wide labor base and should repudiate capitalist reformist politics.
Complicating the situation within the party was an ultra left Trotskyite faction. Known as the Appeal group because of their periodical, Socialist Appeal, the Trotskyites maintained that the Socialist Party should repudiate all labor and farmer labor parties and thus transform itself into a revolutionary party. The Trotskyites also denounced the utilization of democratic means to achieve socialist objectives. From their viewpoint, a revolutionary party needed to resort to violence in order to become a significant political force in America.
These three factions clashed on a variety of issues during the late 1930s. In national convention sessions and local political campaigns, these groups differed over the Socialist Party's attitude toward preventing war, the Socialist Party's affiliation with the American League Against War and Fascism, and socialist cooperation with organized labor. By the end of 1937, the disputes between the various groups were so damaging to the conduct of party business that the National Executive Committee finally took decisive action and expelled the Trotskyite faction.
The Socialist Party never fully recovered from these setbacks, although negotiations were successful in reuniting the Social Democratic Federation with the party in 1957. Nevertheless, despite this encouraging development, the internal conflicts and the emergence of the New Left in the late 1950s and 1960s eventually caused the Socialist Party to lose its influence as an effective political organization.
Scope and Content Note
The Socialist Party Correspondence, 1902-1947, is organized into four geographically-based series, totaling 105 files, many of which do not contain more than 30 items. The materials in this collection relate to the affairs of the Socialist Party's national headquarters and various state branches. In addition to the sizable amount of correspondence, the collection also contains minutes, mimeographed reports, bulletins, constitutions and by laws, financial papers, ephemeral printed matter, circular letters, form letters, political platform statements, lists, resolutions, memoranda, and press releases. Each subject file has been given a frame number and has been cited in the complete reel list which follows this description of the arrangement of the collection.
A representative frame number is IX:23, where the number 23 indicates that this is the 23rd frame (and folder) in the collection, and the Roman numeral IX indicates that the Socialist Party Correspondence is the ninth collection within 19 collections comprising the microfilm set Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956.
The national files have been arranged in chronological order. In some instances, the correspondence for a particular year will precede special subject files for that year in the filming order. For example, the 1919 correspondence (IX:9) precedes the 1919 minutes of the Left Wing Caucus (IX:10) in the filming order. The state files have been arranged in alphabetical order according to the name of the state. In the case of the New York City files, the correspondence for a particular year will precede special subject files for that year in the filming order. For example, as in the national files, the 1933 New York City correspondence (IX:68) precedes the 1933 furriers' union files (IX:69 IX:73) in the filming order. Note that the New York City files follow those for New York State, and precede those for Ohio. The bulk of the collection consists of the New York City and New York State files, respectively.
Series I: National Correspondence(frames IX:1 34) constitute a small portion of this collection. Most of the items in these files pertain to Socialist Party activities in the 1930s, but there are some items for the period, 1907 1929. Of special interest in this section are the following items: Victor Berger's first congressional resolution which called for American neutrality in the Mexican Resolution; papers relating to Socialist Party membership; papers of the National Emergency Convention in 1917 and the Socialist Party response to American participation in World War I; minutes of the Left Wing Caucus and the eventual formation of the American Communist Party; papers pertaining to The Socialist and The Socialist Call; papers relating to the Socialist Party split in the mid 1930s; and resolutions and reports opposing the "Popular Front" of the 1930s. Some of the major correspondents in these files include Daniel W. Hoan, Norman Thomas, August Claessens, James Oneal, Clarence Senior, Paul Porter, David B. Berenberg, John M. Work, William E. Bohn, Julius Gerber, and Theodore Schapiro.
Series II: State Correspondence (excluding New York)(frames IX:35-43) contain information on Socialist Party events in California, Connecticut, Illinois, Indiana, Massachusetts, Michigan, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico, Ohio, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania, Texas, and Wisconsin. The contents of the state files relate primarily to the Socialist Party conflict between the Old Guard and the Militants. The material pertaining to this conflict is quite interesting and offers the scholar a unique insight into how the various branches reacted to this particular development. Other items within these files include papers relating to the controversy surrounding Morris Hillquit's defense of several Russian refugees whose oil fields had been confiscated by the Soviet Union in 1931; minutes of the Dover, New Hampshire local; constitution and by laws of the Ohio branch; an expense record for a Eugene V. Debs Benjamin Hanford Presidential campaign meeting at Philadelphia in 1904; and a letter from Daniel W. Hoan explaining the Wisconsin branch's decision to join, the FarmerLabor Progressive Federation in 1936. The principal correspondents in these state files include Alfred Baker Lewis, Albert Sprague Coolidge, Daniel W. Hoan, and James Oneal.
Series III. The New York State Correspondence(frames IX:44-52) contain materials for the period, 1930 1936. Most of the items relate to the numerous Socialist Party controversies in the mid 1930s, particularly the suspension of the New York State charter by the National Executive Committee in 1935. Again, controversies principally reflect the conflict between the Old Guard and the Militants. Other items in these files pertain to the Erie County local, the 1930 state constitution, and the 1933 New York Socialist Party platform. The major correspondents in these files are Julius Gerber and August Claessens, but there are also letters from Bertha H. Mailly, William C. Duffy, and Louis Waldman.
Series IV: The New York City Correspondence(frames IX:53 98), which follow the New York State files in the filming order, constitute the largest group of records in this collection. Most of these files pertain to events of the 1930s, but there are important items for the 1910s, 1920s, and 1940s as well. of major importance in these files are papers relating to the Socialist Party split and the fur workers dispute. Regarding the party split, there are items pertaining to communist infiltration of the Socialist Party, the suspense of the New York State branch, the militancy of the Young People's Socialist League, and the 1934 Declaration of Principles. The furriers' union papers (IX:69 IX:73) include correspondence from Norman Thomas, minutes of Socialist Party meetings on the "communist" International Fur Workers Union, and the investigative report written by Norman Thomas on the fur workers dispute.
Another interesting aspect of these files are the papers relating to the Women's Committee of the New York City local (IX:74, IX:76, IX:81, IX:88, IX:91). Beginning in 1935, the Women's Committee sponsored a series of meetings known as the "Women's Conference Against the High Cost of Living." These meetings featured speeches by prominent socialists and discussion sessions on such topics as the standard of living, unemployment insurance, social security, socialized medicine, municipal waste, sales taxes, and the Child Labor Amendment. The Women's Committee papers include speeches, outlines, correspondence, and reports regarding these consumer oriented meetings.
Other papers contained in the New York City files relate to such issues and events as the Socialist Party's relationship with organized labor, the 1937 Appeal Clarity group conflict, the differences between communists and socialists concerning the "Popular Front" question, and Socialist Party electoral activities. In the pre 1930 files, there are papers pertaining to the Bronx Agitation Committee, Kings County local, and the East Side Agitation Committee. The major correspondents in these files are Julius Gerber (IX:78, IX:84) and August Claessens (IX:77, IX:83), but there are also numerous letters from William Mailly, W. J. Ghent, Charles Edward Russell, Adolph Germer, Norman Thomas, Alfred Baker Lewis, Jack Altman, Clarence Senior, Esther Friedman, Darlington Hoopes, Mark Starr, Paul Porter, Louis Waldman, Charles Solomon, Daniel W. Hoan, James Oneal, Theodore Schapiro, Dorothy Kenyon, Bertha H. Mailly, and Gerhart Seger.
Arrangement
Within series I, III & IV, folders are arranged chronologically. Within series II, folders are arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
Organized into four series:
I. National Correspondence
II. State Correspondence (excluding New York)
III. New York State Correspondence
IV. New York City Correspondence.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956 (Tamiment Microfilm: Film R-7124.
Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: a guide to the microfilm edition (Sanford, N.C.: Microfilming Corp. of America, c1979), 181 p.
Altman, Jack.; Berenberger, David B.; Bohn, William E.; Claessens, August, 1885-1954; Communist Party of the United States of America.; Coolidge, Albert Sprague, 1894-1977; Duffy, William.; Friedman, Esther.; Gerber, Julius, 1862-1916; Ghent, William J. (William James), 1866-1942.; Hoan, Daniel W. (Daniel Webster), 1881-1961; Hoopes, Darlington, 1896-; International Fur Workers Union of the United States and Canada.; Kenyon, Dorothy, 1888-1972; Lewis, Alfred Baker, 1897-; Mailly, Bertha Howell.; Mailly, William, 1871-1912; Oneal, James, b. 1875.; Rermer, Adolph.; Russell, Charles Edward, 1860-1941; Schapiro, Theodore.; Seger, Gerhart.; Senior, Clarence Ollson, 1903-1974; Solomon, Charles, 1889-1963.; Starr, Mark, 1894-; The socialist call.; The socialist.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968; Waldman, Louis, b. 1892; Work, John M. (John McClelland), 1869-1961.; Bylaws (administrative records).; Communism |z United States; Constitutions.; Minutes.; New York (N.Y.) |x Politics and government |y 20th century.; Popular fronts |z United States.; Press releases.; Resolutions (administrative records); Right and left (Political science); Socialism |z United States.; Women |x Employment |z United States.
- SERIES I: NATIONAL CORRESPONDENCE
  - United States, Aug 1907-May 1908 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:1
  - United States, Mar 1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:2
  - United States, Apr 1911-Nov 1911 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:3
  - United States, Apr 1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:4
  - United States, Jun 1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:5
  - United States, Sep 1913 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:6
  - United States, May 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:7
  - United States: National Emergency Convention, Apr 1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:8
  - United States, May 1919-Oct 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:9
  - United States: Minutes of the Left Wing Caucus, Aug 1919 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:10
  - United States: The Socialist, May 1919-Jun 1919 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:11
  - United States: Debs at Trainmen's Convention, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, Sep 1920 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:12
  - United States: Socialist Convention, Cleveland, Ohio, Apr 1922-Jun 1922 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:13
  - United States: Report to the National Executive Committee, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, May 1926 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:14
  - United States: Election Returns, Nov 1928-[Dec] 1928 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:15
  - United States, May 1929-Aug 1929, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:16
  - United States, May 1931-Dec 1931, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:17
  - United States, ca.Feb 1926, Jan 1932-Nov 1932 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:18
  - United States: Financial Report, Dec 1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:19
  - United States: Membership, Dec 1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:20
  - United States, Jan 1933-Dec 1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:21
  - United States: Membership, Mar 1933 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:22
  - United States, Feb 1934-Dec 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:23
  - United States, Jan 1935-Dec 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:24
  - United States: The Socialist Call, Mar 1933-Aug 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:25
  - United States: Membership, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:26
  - United States: Split, Nov 1935undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:27
  - United States, Jan 1936-Nov 1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:28
  - United States, Mar 1937-May 1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:29
  - United States: "The Stalin Hitler Pact and the International Workers Order", Oct 1939-Nov 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:30
  - United States:, Jan 1940-Dec 1940, ca.Jan 1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:31
  - United States, May 1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:32
  - United States: Bohemian Section, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:33
  - United States, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:34
- SERIES II: STATE CORRESPONDENCE
  - California, Feb 1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:35
  - Connecticut, Mar 1911-Jan 1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:36
  - Illinois, Minutes, May 1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:37
  - Indiana, Aug 1919-Feb 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Film R-7124, Reel 13, Frame IX:38
  - Massachusetts, Feb 1914-Nov 1935 (Box 2, Folder 12)